All right, בוקר טוב, Boker tov, ערב פורים שמח. Erev Purim sameach.
So we pick up with on דף ל Daf lamed and where
are we? Okay, אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, so the line
starts with רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, it's about seven or eight lines
down. So we're dealing with the issue about about which of situations
there's a קנס, knas, there's the fine for a man who rapes
or seduces a young unmarried girl and specifically the issue is about
let's say she's a woman that he's not allowed to marry either
because of an איסור כרת issur kares or an איסור לאו issur
lav and the משנה mishna said even so there is going to
be a קנס knas although the upcoming משנה mishna is going to
say that when it's a חיוב מיתה, chiyuv misa, when it's a
woman that it's actually from prohibited that the punishment would actually be
execution in the court, he would not pay a קנס knas and
we're going to see when we're going to sort of allude to
that in a minute why that would be about. So let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב חסדא
הכל מודים בבועל הנידה, Amar Rav Chisda hakol modim bevo'al hanidda, but
before we get to that even though we've introduced this debate yesterday
about whether a woman who it's אסור assur to marry because of
an איסור לאו issur lav or איסור כרת issur kares is a
קנס, knas, everybody would agree that if the man had sex with
a woman or girl when she was a נידה, משלם קנס, niddah
meshalem knas he does pay a fine even though that was an
איסור כרת issur kares that he just did. So why is that?
ולמאן דאמר יש בה הויה, Uleman d'amar yesh bah havayah, according to
the one that says it has to be a woman that he's
able to marry, okay, well, okay, הא נמי יש בה הויה, ha
nami yesh bah havayah, so קידושין kiddushin you can do קידושין, kiddushin,
a man can do קידושין kiddushin if the woman is a נידה.
nidda, There's a whole interesting question whether you can have נישואין nisu'in
when the woman is a נידה, nidda. can you have חופה chuppah
when the woman is a נידה. nidda, אשכנזים Ashkenazim say yes, ספרדים
Sephardim as a basic rule say no, but that's because נישואין nisu'in
is all about them starting to live together and therefore it's seen
as a virtual type of a like the fact the fact that
they're under the same roof or they're in the same or they're
in like the man's domain, whatever it is or a house, all
of that is supposed to sort of symbolize the fact that they
are now beginning their married life together and their life and the
marital life which is about also having sex together. So therefore if
they're not able to have sex right now, she's a נידה, nidda.
might not count as a woman as נישואין nisu'in and as חופה
chuppah because
but קידושין kiddushin definitely works for a נידה. nidda, So therefore if
there's if the reason is that it might not there might not
be a קנס knas when קידושין kiddushin isn't possible, קידושין kiddushin is
possible in this circumstance, let alone the fact that the status is
a transitory status, but even at this moment קידושין kiddushin is possible.
Okay, ולמאן דאמר ראויה לקיימה, uleman d'amar re'uyah lekayyema, according to the
one that says it's not about whether קידושין kiddushin is binding, but
it's about whether he's allowed to be married to her, so הא
נמי ראויה לקיימה, ha nami re'uyah lekayyema, so according to the whole
man is allowed to be married to a woman when she's a
נידה. nidda. So therefore although a נידה nidda. is an איסור כרת,
issur kares, if it's about the personal status of the person that
might that might exclude her from קנס, knas, that is not relevant
here because the personal status of נידה nidda by no way excludes
her from the concept of marriage, of the bindingness of marriage or
the permissibility of marriage, yes.
So just to get back to something you alluded to, you said
אשכנזים Ashkenazim permit
really let's not talk about that now. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, ולאפוקי מדרבי נחוניא בן הקנה ul'afokei mid'Rabbi
Nechunya ben HaKanah and
now this משנה mishna or maybe this discussion about נידה, nidda there's
a question in רש״י Rashi in terms of how to read this
line, but one way or another this idea that you will pay
a קנס knas even though there's an איסור כרת issur kares because
even though by the נידה nidda, her personal status is that you
can that a man can she can be married, right, but the
act of sex with her is an איסור כרת. issur kares. So
forget the issue of her personal status. Until today we and yesterday
we were discussing exclude the woman because of for her personal status,
a woman that the man isn't allowed to marry or a woman
to whom marriage
isn't
binding. Let's bracket the personal status of the woman. Doesn't matter what
her personal status is. But in the act of rape, he also
did this violation of having sex with let's say a נידה, nidda
okay, which is not a problematic personal status, or any of the
cases in the משנה, mishna, right, and that should be an איסור
כרת issur kares and that איסור כרת issur kares in terms of
the act, not in terms of the person, should override the punishment
the fine of the קנס knas based on קים ליה בדרבה מיניה
kim lei b'dirabba minei and therefore the question is do we say
this? Do we say that an איסור כרת issur kares overrides the
punishment of the קנס knas because as I mentioned to you earlier
our משנה mishna says that you pay for that the קנס. knas.
exist when there's a לאו *lav* or כרת kares, *kares*, but the
next משנה Mishnah *mishnah* is going to say the קנס *knas* does
not exist if there's an איסור issur מיתה misah *issur misah*. So
let's say the woman is, what would be an example of a
חיוב chiyuv מיתה misah *chiyuv misah*? We'd have to look at the
next משנה *mishnah*. A mother. Let's say it's his mother. Okay, his
mother wouldn't
be... that wouldn't work. His daughter. Okay, let's say it's his daughter.
Okay? So therefore, in that case, okay, he wouldn't pay קנס *knas*.
Why not? I mean, if you pay קנס *knas* even if you
can't marry the woman... himself. Let's not worry about... Okay, fine, whatever,
we'll figure it out. Anyway, if you pay a קנס *knas* even
if you marry... even if... even if... even if you can't marry
the woman, why not pay a קנס *knas* in the case where
it's a חיוב chiyuv מיתה *chiyuv misah*? So clearly that's on the
principle of קים ליה Kim lei, בדרבה מיניה *kim lei bidrabah minei*.
That if it's an act that is deserving of execution in the
court, that overrides any monetary payment. So the question we're going to
focus on is fine, that's what our משנה *mishnah* assumes when it's
something that's deserving of execution. What about if it's something that's an
איסור כרת issur kareis *issur kares*? Our משנה *mishnah* assumes that that
does not... that does not trigger קים ליה Kim lei. *kim lei*.
So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to introduce, or we'll see,
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to introduce an opinion that says
it does. Okay, so let's take a look. ולאפוקי *ula'appukei*, so this
discussion about נדה *niddah* that there will be a קנס *knas*, or
basically our general assumption in our משנה *mishnah* that there's a קנס
*knas* by an איסור כרת issur kares, *issur kares*, is coming to
exclude, to reject the position of רבי נחוניא בן הקנה Rebbe Nechunya
ben HaKana. *Rebbi Nechunyah ben Hakanah*. Of רבי נחוניא בן הקנה *Rebbi
Nechunyah ben Hakanah* who says that even in a case of כרת
kares *kares* we say קים ליה kim lei בדרבה מיניה *kim lei
bidrabah minei*. דתניא *de-tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא *Baraita*: רבי נחוניא
בן הקנה היה עושה יום הכפורים כשבת לתשלומין *Rebbi Nechunyah ben Hakanah
hayah oseh Yom HaKippurim ke-Shabbos le-tashlumin*. רבי נחוניא בן הקנה *Rebbi Nechunyah
ben Hakanah*, he would say that יום כפור *Yom Kippur* would be
like שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* when it comes to having to pay. What
does this mean? So there's a classic case if you burn down
somebody's haystack on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*, you don't have to pay. Because
the very act that made you liable for damages, the burning of
the haystack, was an act of חילול שבת chilul Shabbos *chilul Shabbos*.
And therefore the act of חילול שבת chilul Shabbos *chilul Shabbos* overrides
the act of damages. That's the principle of קים ליה kim lei
*kim lei*. And he's right. And well, that's a discussion. And חילול
שבת chilul Shabbos *chilul Shabbos* is something that is punishable by execution.
So רבי נחוניא בן הקנה *Rebbi Nechunyah ben Hakanah* said it would
be the same thing if you burned down his haystack on יום
כפור *Yom Kippur*. Even though that's punishable by כרת kares, *kares*, not
by execution, it would have the same effect of overriding the liability
for payment. Okay. מה שבת Shabbat, מתחייב בנפשו פטור patur, מן התשלומין
אף יום הכפורים מתחייב בנפשו פטור מן התשלומין *mah Shabbos mitchayev be-nafsho
patur min ha-tashlumin, af Yom HaKippurim mitchayev be-nafsho patur min ha-tashlumin*. The
same way on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* when you did something that you
are liable for your very life, you did something that is deserving
of the death penalty, you're exempt from תשלומין Tashlumim. *tashlumin*, even on
יום כפור *Yom Kippur* if you do something that is liable for
your life because you know, כרת kares, *kares* is your soul even
if it's not your physical life, so equally that would exempt you
from payment. Now, logically, this obviously is a big jump. Besides just
the fact that the idea of קים ליה Kim leh *kim lei*
is a big enough חידוש chiddush *chiddush* as it is, and maybe
we only say it in the most severe cases and not in
the cases that are less severe, but it's also a big jump
because קים ליה Kim leh *kim lei* presumably has to do with
the punishments that the court imposes. That since the court is going
to impose, or can impose in some cases, a punishment of execution,
therefore, you know, it's sort of like... it's sort of like, you
know, I mean it is true in American court, for example, like
OJ Simpson got off in terms of the, you know, in terms
of murder but then he was tried in civil court. Okay, but
you can sort of understand, like, you got to make your decision
how you want to prosecute this case. Are you going to prosecute
this case as a murder trial or are you going to prosecute
this case as damages? Right? So you can sort of understand that
if in terms of the בית דין *beit din*, it's a weightier
case, it's a חילול שבת Chilul Shabbos, *chilul Shabbos* case, it doesn't
get to be prosecuted as a מזיק mazik. *mazik* case. Okay, so
that's like one way of understanding it. But if it's something that
the weightier thing is only between the person and God, it's an
איסור כרת issur kares. *issur kares*, then why should that be relevant
for the בית דין *beit din* prosecuting the civil case? Right? Very
nice that you're חייב chayav *chayav* to כרת kares *kares* because you
were מחלל *mechallel* יום כפור *Yom Kippur*. What does that have to
do with us? As far as we're concerned, all we see here
that's relevant for our docket, for our case, is the fact that
you burned down this guy's, you know, haystack. So saying his idea
is definitely a big חידוש *chiddush*, not just because כרת kares *kares*
is not as weighty, but because כרת kares *kares* isn't an issue
about the court. So to say קים ליה Kim leh *kim lei*
in that type of a case is definitely a bigger חידוש *chiddush*.
Now, I do want to tell you something. I might be introducing
too many ideas at this stage, but might as well just get
it over with, is that the idea of קים ליה Kim leh
*kim lei*, certainly in a case of let's say a capital case
like חילול שבת Chilul Shabbos. *chilul Shabbos*,
generally is... applies, I mean there's debates about some of these things,
but anyway, even if the חילול שבת chillul Shabbos *chilul Shabbos*, even
if you're not actually going to prosecute the guy. Let's say for
example there were no witnesses. Okay? Or let's say they didn't give
him התראה *hasra'ah*, they didn't give him a warning. Or let's say
he was שוגג *shogeg*. Let's say he wasn't intentional in his חילול
שבת Shabbos, *chilul Shabbos*. It could still be, or really still is,
according to... that... that he... that he still doesn't pay the fine.
Because since it's a type of a case of a capital crime,
even if it's not prosecutable as such, we can't prosecute it because
he didn't do it intentionally or there were technical issues or so
on, still the nature of the act was a capital crime and
that over... overshadows anything else. But again, that's very different to say
a חיוב chiyuv מיתה *chiyuv misah* that cannot be prosecuted as opposed
to something... In principle is never an issue of the court and
is only a חיוב chiyuv, כרת. karei And that's the חידוש of
רבי נחוניא בן הקנה. So let's take a look.
What if it was let's say fire came from his fireplace and
he had nothing to do with it, he wouldn't be,
of course, and he's not doing an act. Okay, so אף יום
הכיפורים מתחייב בנפשו פטור מן התשלומים. Af Yom HaKippurim mis-chayev b'nafsho patur
min hatashlumim. מאי טעמא דרבי נחוניא בן הקנה? Mai ta'ama d'Rebbe Nechunya
ben HaKana? What's the reasoning? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, נאמר אסון בידי
אדם. Ne'emar ason b'yedei adam. It speaks about an accident occurring or
a tragedy occurring, and that's when it happens through people, because it
says אם אסון יהיה ונתת נפש תחת נפש. Im ason yihyeh venasata
nefesh tachas nafesh. And this is actually to be one of the
basis for the idea of קים ליה, Kim leh right? It says
if two men are fighting and one man smites a woman that's
standing by and she's pregnant, and if לא יהיה אסון, lo yihyeh
ason, if there's no אסון, ason, then you actually pay the fine.
But אם אסון יהיה, im ason yihyeh, you don't pay the fine,
you rather נפש תחת נפש. nefesh tachas nafesh. You pay for you
know with your life. So what does אסון ason and לא אסון
lo ason mean? So the חז"ל Chazal understand that אסון ason means
that that it's that that a actual not the fetus is killed
but actual a you know a the one of the adults there,
one of the living people is killed or somebody doesn't have to
be an adult but whatever. So if actually a born person is
already killed, then you're not going to pay for the fetus, then
it's going to be the crime of murder and you're going to
pay with it for your life. But the important thing for us
is you're not going to pay for the fetus that gets killed
in the in the process. Okay, that even though the the you
know the miscarriage of the fetus is normally something that entails a
fine, if there's a death of a person that has already been
born, if there's a death in the process, then there's not going
to be a fine, there's going to be a capital crime of
murder. So that actually tells us the principle of קים ליה. kim
lei, So and that's a case where a human being causes this
action, this tragedy. ונאמר V'ne'emar and it says by יעקב Yaakov and
and בנימין Binyamin אסון, ason, right? I don't want to send him
down because some אסון ason will occur on the way, some tragedy
will occur. בידי שמים Biydei shamayim and that means something that happens
not through human agency but God brings it about. Okay, it's natural
causes. מה אסון האמור בידי אדם פטור מן התשלומים? Ma ason ha'amur
b'yedei adam patur min hatashlumim? So the same way in the case
when it's a human act that was tragic that led to a
death, therefore you're exempt from payment, that's the case of the miscarriage
and somebody dies, אף אסון האמור בידי שמים פטור מן התשלומים. Af
ason ha'amur b'yedei shamayim patur min hatashlumim.
Similarly, if it's a type of a death that God brings about,
a כרת, kareis a death of the soul in when it's an
act that brought that about, that would also exempt somebody from payment.
Of course, it's a little bit funny because the אסון ason in
one case is not that the doer, the perpetrator, is getting this
human death, the death of the court, it's that he brought about
the death of another person, whereas we're trying to apply it to
a case of כרת kareis where God is bringing about is is
imposing you know a death of the soul on the perpetrator. So
it's not obviously it's not exactly שייכא. shaycha. But anyway, that's what
he says. The idea of אסון ason here being something brought about
God teaches me that even if it's a sin that is only
deserving of punishment from God, of כרת, Kares of an excision of
the soul, that that also would be exempt from payment. מתיב ליה
רב אבא בר אבא, Masiv lei Rav Abba bar Abba, so רב
אבא בר אבא Rav Abba bar Abba asks on this. מאי דכי
קמזהר ליה יעקב לבניי אצינים ופחים בידי שמים נינהו? Mai d'chi k'mazhar
lei Yaakov livnei atzinim upachim b'yedei shamayim ninhu?
How do you know that this אסון ason by בנימין Binyamin when
יעקב Yaakov is warning his children, that it's referring to the type
of a natural causes of of cold and and heat that all
comes from God? צנים ופחים Tzinim upachim yeah, פחים pachim I know,
you think פחים pachim means a like a like a pit, like
like or a trap, but רש"י Rashi tells us both say that
it could mean that but it also here means means heat cold
weather and hot weather. דילמא אאריא וגנבי דבידי אדם נינהו? Dilma a'arya
u'ganvei d'biydei adam ninhu?
Maybe it's about lions and thieves that something through human agency? Now
you're saying what, lions, human agency? So what you have to understand
here is is that the גמרא Gemara is not just is not
just assuming that the question is as to whether it's a natural
cause or a human cause, meaning that the basic category is human
and anything that's not human is defined as בידי שמים, b'yedei shamayim,
as natural. No, the גמרא Gemara is doing the opposite. It's assuming
that בידי שמים b'yedei shamayim means an assumption that God is going
to bring it about, some type of a providential punishment. Okay, so
if something happens to you and it's בידי שמים, b'yedei shamayim, it
doesn't mean it's natural and it's random. If something happens to you
and it's בידי שמים, b'yedei shamayim, it means God brought it about.
So בידי אדם b'yedei adam is seen as anything that God didn't
bring about, that was just because of the natural way the world
works, whether it's through human agency or through bad luck or through
negligence or whatever it might be. One minute. So let's just get
through this. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, so how do
you know that the that יעקב Yaakov was afraid, right? Because again,
the idea of בידי שמים b'yedei shamayim is כרת, Kares and כרת
Kares is not just natural causes, כרת Kares is something that is
a punishment from God. So how do you know that when יעקב
Yaakov was commanding his kids, אצינים ופחים בידי שמים נינהו, atzinim upachim
b'yedei shamayim ninhu, it was about issues of of you know very
hot weather or cold weather that would be something that God would
have brought about and therefore similar to the כרת Kares idea? דילמא
Dilma אם על אריה וגנבי בידי אדם נינהו, im al aryeh ve-ganvei
biyadei adam ninhu,
maybe it's about lions and thieves which is something that is again
not human agency but not necessarily divinely brought about and therefore it's
not the category of things that are divinely brought about that יעקב
Yaakov is talking about. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. אטו,
atu, one second. יעקב הא אזהר הא לא אזהר? Yaakov ha azhir
ha lo azhir? What? You think יעקב Yaakov saying oh I'm only
worried about one type of tragedy not another type of tragedy?
יעקב הא מכולהו אזהר. Yaakov ha mi-kuleihu azhir. יעקב Yaakov is warning
about all types of tragedies. So when he says lest an אסון
ason occur, it means whatever the reason of the אסון ason is,
whether it's something that God is bringing about, whether it's something that
comes through humans or natural causes. But since his אסון ason incorporates
all types of tragedies, it also includes those that God brings about.
And therefore those are put in the same category. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says, now the גמרא Gemara has a fun little
digression and the
גמרא Gemara says like this: וצנים ופחים בידי שמים נינהו? u-tzinim u-pachim
biyadei shamayim ninhu?
You mean to tell me hot and cold weather or whatever those
are things that are like directly punishments that are brought about by
God? והתניא ותנא ברייתא הכל בידי שמים ve-ha-tanya u-tana baraita ha-kol biyadei
shamayim
everything comes from God in terms of like you know bad things
that happen to us or good things חוץ מצנים ופחים chutz mitzinim
u-pachim and except for, except for global warming, very, written very nicely
said, except for the hot weather and cold weather. Now what does
that mean? If anything you would say is not something under our
control besides Dov's cute comment about global warming, it would be the
weather. So yes, the weather does come from God but right the
effect that it has on you, don't that is not something that
God is bringing about. והתניא הכל בידי שמים חוץ מצנים ופחים שנאמר
צנים פחים בדרך עקש. ve-hatanya ha-kol biyadei shamayim chutz mitzinim u-pachim she-ne'emar
tzinim pachim be-derech itkesh.
So again this might mean more like you know like traps and
pits or whatever but again I understand because it talks about בדרך,
be-derech, on the path. But the גמרא Gemara anyway the גמרא Gemara
isn't clear but רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos are reading this to
be cold and hot. Okay, cold and heat are on the path
of the, of a you know of the perverted. שומר נפשו ירחק
מהם. shomer nafsho yirchak me-hem. Somebody who's able to watch themselves, take
care of yourself, you can you know bundle up, put on a
hat if it's cold outside you know and therefore don't stand directly
in the sun, go in the shade, don't you know die of
dehydration and then say it was God's fault. Okay so basically so
it's of course what it's a funny message. So what that sort
of means is is that is that God is not going like
other things you can also avoid right so what does it mean
הכל בידי שמים? ha-kol biyadei shamayim? Like so everything else I can't
avoid? So you know... גנבי והאריה... ganvei ve-ha-aryeh... right like
locking up my house for from the גנבים? ganavim? That that I
can't avoid? The only thing that I can avoid is the hot
and the cold? So תוספות Tosfos says I mean it's hard to
exactly get what the גמרא Gemara is getting at. תוספות Tosfos says
what the גמרא Gemara is trying to say is is that that
if God wants to bring about a punishment onto you right then
he can do it through all types of means. Yes it's true
very often bad things can happen to you because you're negligent yourself
and you could have watched yourself about it and it's all your
own fault or it's all random. Sure a lot of things happen
because they're random or because of your negligence. But if God wants
to bring about punishment on you then he'll bring it about through
other means and there's no way you're going to escape it you
know God will see that it happens. Except for God will never
bring out heat and cold as a way to direct punishment towards
you because that's and because this פסוק pasuk teaches us that that's
something that you could always take the right measures to escape and
God won't sort of override those measures. All right so go figure
that out it's hard to exactly you know sort of get what
the גמרא Gemara is getting at but that's the way תוספות Tosfos
understands it. All right so everything God can you know will use
all different means to bring about divinely ordained punishments except for צנים
ופחים. tzinim u-pachim. That's always going to be random and it's always
going to be something that's in your hand to prevent. Okay. ותו?
ve-tu? So that's in terms of saying so why are you calling
צנים ופחים tzinim u-pachim בידי שמים biyadei shamayim if anything that's the
most that's בידי אדם. biyadei adam. ותו, ve-tu, and in addition: אריה
וגנבי בידי אדם נינהו? aryeh ve-ganvei biyadei adam ninhu? Are you telling
me lions and thieves are something that is not directed from God?
והאמר רב יוסף וכן תני דבי רבי חייא: ve-ha-amar Rav Yosef ve-chen
tani d'vei Rabbi Chiyya:
מיום שחרב בית המקדש, mi-yom she-charav Beit Ha-Mikdash, from the time that
the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash was destroyed, אף על פי שבתלו סנהדרין,
af-al-pi she-batlu Sanhedrin, although there is no longer a סנהדרין Sanhedrin dealing
with cases of execution, ארבע מיתות לא בטלו. arba mitot lo batlu.
The four types of execution did not stop, they were still imposed.
So גמרא Gemara, says: לא בטלו? lo batlu? The four types of
court execution were not did not cease? הא בטלו להו! ha batlu-lu!
What do you mean they did cease? אלא, ella, what it means
is: דין ארבע מיתות לא בטלו. din arba mitot lo batlu.
The punishment that parallels the four, you know that sort of divinely
ordained punishment that is come as a type of a parallel for
these four executions did not cease. So you think you're going to
get out of it because oh you know there's no court around
to prosecute you don't worry God is going to get you in
the end. מי שנתחייב סקילה, mi she-nitchayev sekilah, somebody who is deserving
of stoning, או נופל מן הגג או חיה דורסתו. o nofel min
ha-gag o chaya dores-to. Either he'll fall from a roof because you
know they would stone a person they basically would throw him over
a cliff is how the גמרא Gemara understood what stoning was and
then they put a stone on him so either you'd fall off...
fall off a roof or an animal would trample him because then
the body would like shatter at the bottom, so that would be
parallel to stoning. ומי שנתחייב שריפה, Umi she'nischayav sreifa, somebody deserving of
being of being burned, you know,
execution by fire, which basically according to the rabbis would be pouring
molten lead down his throat. או נופל בדליקה, o nofel bidleika, but
here it's more literal, so he would either be you know caught
in a burning building. או נחש מכישו, o nachash mkisho, or a
the venom a snake would bite him and the venom of a
snake would be like burning. ומי שנתחייב הריגה, umi she'nischayav hariga, somebody
deserving of execution by the sword. או נמסר למלכות, o nimsar lamalchus,
he's either given over to the Roman government that will execute you
by the sword. או
ליסטים באים עליו, o listim bo'im alav, or thieves, bandits will come
and kill the guy by the sword. ומי שנתחייב חנק, umi she'nischayav
chenek, and somebody deserving of strangulation. או טובע בנהר, o toveia banahar,
will either drown in the in the river so he'll like you
know he'll choke to death.
Right, exactly. או מת בסרונכי, o meis bisrunki, this is a really
cute גמרא, Gemara או מת בסרונכי o meis bisrunki or will die
with some type of a respiratory ailment that he'll basically won't be
able to breathe. So basically you see what you it's the exact
reverse of what you said. Cold and heat is not you know
is not divinely directed
and גנבים ganavim and lions is divinely directed. So the גמרא Gemara
says okay. So the גמרא Gemara says fine. אלא איפוך, ela ifoch,
fine, so you want to reverse it, reverse it. חיה וגנבי בידי
שמים, chaya v'ganavei bidei shamayim, צינים ופחים בידי אדם, tzinim u'pachim bidei
adam, fine. The lions and the and the and the thieves are
divinely directed and the cold and the heat is your own fault.
Either way says the גמרא Gemara the point is that when יעקב
Yaakov says וקראהו אסון v'karahu ason he's talking not just about human
imposed types of tragedies and death, he's even talking about ones that
are natural or ones that come from God which we understand to
be talking about divinely directed ones. And therefore it's all in the
same category and the same way the court execution exempts a person
from punishment then similarly a divinely ordained type of a כרת Kares
of the soul will also excuse a person from punishment. Little תוספות
Tosafot here that asks the question of does this really work by
the way in terms of these divinely ordained punishments. If you look
at תוספות Tosafot top of here ל"א
ע"ב. lamed-alef amud-beis. דין ארבע מיתות לא בטלו. din arba misos lo
batlu. ואם תאמר והאמר בשמעתא דפועלים v'im tomar v'ha'amar bishmatta de'poalim דההוא
דזקפוהו אף על פי שהיה חייב סקילה de'hahu d'zakfuhu af al pi
she'haya chayav skila
wait a minute no no that's not the one I wanted to
see.
Yeah it says like this. אבל קשה aval kasha the last the
fourth line in the תוספות Tosafot the last of the wide lines
from the top. אבל קשה דחזינן כמה עברייני aval kasha de'chazinan kama
avaryani we see a lot of sinners ועובדי עבודת כוכבים v'ovdei avodas
kochavim okay שמתים על מיטותיהם she'meisim al mitoseihem that they die you
know in peace they they they die in their bed you know
happy and prosperous and so on. So like this is the age
old question right about צדיק ורע לו רשע וטוב
לו. tzadik v'ra lo rasha v'tov lo. So they you know what
happened did you did you like did you forget the beginning of
גמרא ברכות Gemara Berachos which spends like three דפין dappin trying to
figure out that things don't work as nicely as they're supposed to
work. ויש לומר v'yeish lomar let's see what תוספות Tosafot the answer
is to this to this philosophical theological question that's been with us
for millennia. Right. So you understand this does say something by the
way about the nature of the rabbinic enterprise right. So the question
about like about נידה nidda, משלם קנס meshallem knas, and בעולה לכהן
גדול beulah l'kohen gadol you know
they get like this amount of space. The question for this profound
religious theological question of why do the why do the wicked prosper
gets two lines in תוספות. Tosafot.
It's a war in its own time.
So ויש לומר v'yeish lomar okay it's a legal tradition what do
you want. ויש לומר דעל ידי תשובה הקדוש ברוך הוא מקיל v'yeish
lomar d'al yedei teshuva Hakadosh Baruch Hu makeil ולפעמים מוחל לגמרי u'l'famim
mochel legamrei או זכות תולה לו o zchus tola lo ואינו נפרע
ממנו
בחייו. v'eino nifra mimenu bechayav. Alright you don't know who's really righteous
who's really whatever maybe he's get he did תשובה teshuva maybe he
had a good deed that's being paid off God is paying him
off in this world so that he can get punished in the
next world. So there's a whole bunch of חשבונות cheshbonos that we
don't understand. Okay so anyway that's your answer to that theological question.
Yes.
תוספות Tosafot changes עבודות avodot from to עבודה
זרה. avoda zara.
Ah yes actually yeah clearly. Alright so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay so basically we have the idea of רב נחוניא בן הקנה
Rav Nechunya ben Hakana that if somebody is חייב כרת chayav kareis
like burns down a haystack on יום כיפור Yom Kippur that they
don't have to pay the fine. Similarly if a man if a
man rapes or seduces a woman who's a נידה niddah let alone
a woman who's like איסור כרת issur kares like a sister and
so on but even if there's no issue with her personal status
since the act was done with a in a way that he
was deserving of כרת Kares according to רב נחוניא בן הקנה Rav
Nechunya ben Hakana that would override the fine and he would be
exempt from the fine that is not the position of our משנה
that is the position of רב נחוניא בן הקנה. Rav Nechunya ben
Hakana. Okay and the question is do you say this קים ליה
kim lei. idea by things that are divinely ordained punishments but are
not an issue for the court. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
רבא אמר טעמא דרב נחוניא בן הקנה מהכא. Rava amar tama d'Rav
Nechunya ben Hakana meihacha. The reason רב נחוניא בן הקנה Rav Nechunya
ben Hakana comes from here:
ואם העלם יעלימו עם הארץ את עיניהם. v'im haleim ya'alimu am ha'aretz
es eineihem. This seems to be a much more relevant פסוק pasuk
although it's not itself about קים ליה Kim lei, but it does
connect the two ideas of כרת Kares and מיתת בית דין. misas
beis din. This is talking about somebody that is deserving of that
did עבודה זרה avoda zara and is deserving to be put to
death.
over to the מלך Molech and ובלתי המית אותו u'vilti hamito oto
I think is the end of the פסוק pasuk and they do
not execute him like they're supposed to then it says ושמתי אני
את פניי באיש ההוא ובמשפחתו v'samti ani et panai ba'ish ha'hu u'v'mishpachto
I will pay my attention to this man and to his family
והכרתי אותו מקרב עמו v'hichratti oto mikerev ammo and I will like
excise him from his nation so basically God is saying if you
guys don't do your job to execute him don't worry then not
don't worry but you should know that he's going to get כרת
Kares from me he's going to get cut off from me so
there that's much more directly relevant the execution of the court the
substitute for the execution of the court is is God giving כרת
Kares okay so that's if whatever's true about execution of the court
is true about God's כרת Kares so
how does it show קים ליה Kim lei
well it's not about קים ליה Kim lei that's what I said
the פסוק pasuk of אסון ason was about קים ליה Kim lei.
this is not itself about קים ליה Kim lei but it is
much more directly about that God's כרת Kares is a substitute for
the court's execution as a general
idea but אסון ason would be human beings are going to abdicate
their responsibility
okay so that's true meaning what you could say
is right what you could say
right so thank you so that is true what you could say
is fine so if somebody did like I said before חילול שבת
Shabbos. and we don't execute him then his divine punishment will be
a substitute and we're not going to impose the fine but still
the sin that he did was חילול שבת Shabbos and was deserving
of מיתת בית דין misas Beis Din so Rav Dov is absolutely
correct that this does not prove a parallel to a case where
you're only deserving of כרת Kares this is a case where the
person is deserving of a court execution but he just isn't going
to get prosecuted by the court okay so that's absolutely correct קים
ליה
Kim
lei means we establish him בדרבא מיניה b'drabba minei in what is
the greater one in the greater punishment which is
we haven't seen that לשון lashon
I know we haven't seen it it's the principle here but we
have not seen it yet we'll see it okay so אמר תורה
amar Torah כרת שלי כמיתה שלכם Kares sheli k'misah shelachem
my כרת Kares is like your execution מה מיתה שלכם פטור מן
התשלומים mah misah shelachem patur min hatashlumin
the same way when you impose an execution he's exempt from payment
אף כרת שלי פטור מן התשלומים af Kares sheli patur min hatashlumin
even my כרת Kares the guy is exempt from an execution and
Rav Dov correctly says you know what really you learn from this
is that if the guy was מחלל שבת m'chalel Shabbos and we
didn't actually execute him there weren't witnesses there wasn't warning it was
בשוגג b'shogeg or בשוגג b'shogeg doesn't even get כרת Kares but anyway
but at least there you could say whatever punishment he's going to
get from God that's parallel and therefore he'll be off the hook
it really is not a good application to a case where the
whole thing was never in the category of a court execution was
only in the category of כרת kares like the case of יום
כיפור Yom Kippur or the case of sister you know a brother
and sister and so on okay but those are the two דרשות
drashos by the way just an interesting parenthetical point באיש ההוא ובמשפחתו
ba'ish ha'hu u'v'mishpachto is very interesting that man and his family like
the whole idea about like collective punishment right if the man sinned
how did his family sin and you know and so רש"י Rashi
immediately says well cause you never have a case where somebody is
not being enabled by the by his family members and they know
and they keep him quiet and interestingly Onkelos translates this as that
man and his and his colleagues
I think it says or his supporters I have to I have
to I don't remember the exact terminology let me take a look
what is it ויקרא Vayikra what is it 20 chapter
verse 4 and
5 20 verse
what 4 and
5 בגברא ההוא ובסעדוהי b'gavra ha'hu u'v'sa'adohi and that man and his
and those that enable him those that support him so might be
based on רש"י Rashi but at least he's not saying that we
assume that the family are his enablers right it specifically means those
that are his
supporters or משפחה mishpacha like
the it's used in a figurative sense right whatever okay anyway all
right so those are the two דרשות drashos either it's learned from
אסון ason by יעקב Yaakov or it's learned from this case about
if the court doesn't execute God will give כרת kares. so now
the גמרא Gemara says מאי איכא בין רבא לאביי mai ikka bein
Rava l'Abaye what's the difference between whether you base it on the
אסון ason idea or the כרת kares. idea so the גמרא Gemara
says איכא בינייהו זר שאכל תרומה ikka beinaihu zar she'achal trumah if
a non-כהן Kohen eats תרומה trumah and he eats the תרומה trumah
of a כהן Kohen that isn't his so in that act of
eating he is both stealing and doing a sin that is חייב
מיתה בידי שמיים chayav misah bidei Shamayim eating תרומה trumah is חייב
מיתה בידי שמיים chayav misah bidei Shamayim now what you have to
understand is that חייב מיתה בידי שמיים chayav misah bidei Shamayim although
if you ask me that sounds weightier than כרת kares, because it
has the word מיתה in it כרת kares is more abstract but
חז"ל Chazal understand that that's actually less weighty than כרת kares, why
is it less weighty רש"י Rashi says כרת karet, also implies the
death of the children whereas מיתה does not תוספות Tosafot disagrees he
thinks only ערירי ariri implies the death of the children but whatever
it means the assumption is that מיתה בידי שמיים misah bidei Shamayim
is less severe than כרת so what if it's deserving of a
divine punishment but less
The guy ate תרומה truma that wasn't his. אביי פטור. Abaye patur.
According to אביי, Abaye, he'd still be exempt from payment because he
learns it out from אסון. ason. So any divinely ordained punishment, whether
it's כרת or מיתה בידי שמים, misa bidei shamayim, gets him off
the hook for payment. ולרבא חייב, U'leRava chayav, according to רבא Rava
you'd be חייב chayav because רבא Rava only it has to be
at the level of כרת. He learns that from a פסוק pasuk
about כרת. Okay.
So now we've established the idea of רב נחוניא בן הקנה Rav
Nechunya ben HaKana who applies it by כרת, and we've had a
discussion about whether it's כרת or does it even include מיתה בידי
שמים. misa bidei shamayim. And now the גמרא Gemara is going to
a little bit shift gears. Let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says ולאביי פטור, U'leAbaye patur, are you really exempt according to
אביי Abaye in this case of eating תרומה? truma? והאמר רב חסדא,
Veha'amar Rav Chisda, מודה רב נחוניא בן הקנה modeh Rav Nechunya ben
HaKana בגונב חלבו begonev chelvo של חבירו, shel chaveiro, or חלבו, chelbo,
חלבו, chelvo, חלב, chelev, what would be חלבו? chelbo? I think it's
חלב.
chelev. חלב. chelev.
חלבו. chelbo. חלבו. chelbo. חלבו. chelbo. Right, חלבו chalavo would be his
milk, right? Okay, חלבו chelbo של חבירו shel chaveiro ואכלו, ve'achalo, שהוא
חייב, she'hu chayav, שכבר נתחייב בגניבה shekevar nitchayav bigniva קודם שבא לידי
איסור חלב. kodem sheba lidei issur chelev. So now the גמרא Gemara
is putting aside for a moment the question about how weighty of
a sin it has to be. Fine, כרת, מיתה בידי שמים, misa
bidei shamayim, מיתה בידי אדם, misa bidei adam, whatever it is. Now
we're going to get into some of the really like
precise definitions of when it's seen that these two things one overshadows
the other. And how much do they have to be the same
act or not the same act? All the cases we've been given,
right, having sex with, raping his sister-in-law or his sister, whatever it
would
be, the act of sex is the act that's חייב כרת chayav
kares and the act that you pay the fine. Burning down the
haystack is the act that you're חייב chayav for חילול שבת Shabbos.
and the act of מזיק. mazik But if there are separate acts,
then you don't say one overshadows the other, then they're two separate
acts and each one is prosecuted separately. Okay, so let's see the
application of that. If somebody steals his friend's חלב chelev and then
eats it, that he has to pay. You don't say קים ליה,
Kim lei even though the eating of חלב chelev is an איסור
issur, כרת, שכבר נתחייב בגניבה shekevar nitchayav bigniva קודם שבא לידי איסור
חלב, kodem sheba lidei issur chelev, because he was obligated to pay
for the fine before he did the sin of eating the fat,
which is an איסור כרת. Okay, אלמא, alman, you see, דבעידנא דאגבהיה,
de'be'idana de'agbei'ah, from the moment he lifted up the חלב, chelev, קניה,
kanyei, he acquires it, meaning and it's the act of stealing and
he's liable to pay for it. נתחייב בנפשו לא הוי עד דאכליה,
nitchayav benafsho lo havai ad de'achlei,
but he's not liable for his soul, he didn't do the איסור
כרת until he ate it. So
here too, בעידנא דאגבהיה קניה, be'idana de'agbei'ah kanyei, when he takes the
תרומה truma from his friend the כהן Kohen house, he stole it
and he's חייב chayav in payment. נתחייב בנפשו לא הוי עד דאכליה.
nitchayav benafsho lo havai ad de'achlei. So
and he doesn't do the איסור of that's חייב מיתה בידי שמים
chayav misa bidei shamayim until he eats it. So how do you
get the two being the same act? They're different acts and therefore
there's no principle of קים ליה. Kim lei So the גמרא Gemara
says, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bemai askinan, כגון שדחבו חבירו לתוך פיו.
kegon she'dechavo chaveiro letoch piv. Ah,
so what we're doing is, now the גמרא Gemara gets into these
fine like crazy scenarios in order to make things happen at the
same time. Your friend stuck the תרומה truma into your mouth. So
you never lifted it up. And since you didn't lift it up,
you didn't steal it until you ate it. So the act of
eating was the act of being מזיק mazik it, and it was
the act that you're חייב מיתה, chayav misa, but you didn't steal
it prior. So the גמרא Gemara says,
סוף סוף, sof sof, כיון דלעסיה
קניה, keivan dile'asei kanyei, when you chew it then you've acquired it.
I mean now you could say it seems more like an act
of מזיק mazik, than an act of גניבה, gniva, but you could
also say that if it's on your body that's like taking possession.
So the same way taking it in your hand is an act
of גניבה gniva or גזילה, gzaila, so even if I didn't put
it on my body, keeping it on my body and taking possession
of it by chewing, right, that's an act of גניבה. gniva. So
either it's גניבה gniva or מזיק, mazik, but either way when you
chew it, then you are חייב chayav for payment. Let me just
finish this, נתחייב בנפשו לא הוי עד דבלעיה, nitchayav benafsho lo havai
ad de'balyei, but you're only but it's not considered an act of
eating תרומה truma by chewing. An איסור, something that you're not allowed
to eat, you only transgress when you actually swallow.
Right, so
when you chew it, you've done an act of either גניבה gniva
or מזיק, Mazik and when you swallow it, you've done an act
of eating תרומה, truma, so they're not coming at the same time,
so one should not overshadow the other. Yes, Dove, you had something.
No, I was going to say so the minute you chew, the
minute you chomp down, you could say that you are simultaneously causing
נזק nezek and being קונה koneh the object, but it's not בידי
שמים bidei shamayim issue. Right, it's not a חיוב תרומה, chiyuv truma,
exactly.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says you still don't have it at
the same time. So the גמרא Gemara says, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha
bemai askinan, כגון שדחבו לו לתוך בית הבליעה. kegon she'dechavo lo letoch
beis habliah. Okay, what your friend did is he stuck the food
into your throat, not just into your mouth, into your throat. Now,
okay, so therefore the act of swallowing the גמרא Gemara is going
to assume, the act of swallowing is an act of eating. No,
if the act of swallowing is forced, then you're not חייב chayav,
for it. But no, it got into your throat forced, but now
you are choosing to swallow. So why isn't your friend חייב, chayev?
he's the one that took it? All right, so that רש"י Rashi
and תוספות Tosfos discuss. We'll talk about that in a minute, but
let's just focus on what the גמרא Gemara is saying. And therefore
now when you choose to swallow, the exact act of swallowing is
an act of מזיק Mazik, or גניבה Gneiva and it's also an
act of what do you call it of eating תרומה. Truma. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, the גמרא Gemara says like this:
היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אי דמצי לאהדורה, Ei dematzi
leahadura, if you can spit it out now that it's in your
throat, נהדר, nahadar, so spit it back out. אי לא מצי לאהדורה
Ei lo matzi leahadura and if you can't spit it out, אמאי
חייב, amai chayav, why are you חייב? chayev Now the second part
of the question makes sense, right? If you can't spit it out,
if all you can do is swallow it because physically you can't
get it out of your throat unless somebody let's say performs the
Heimlich maneuver and maybe even not then, right, so then you can't
say that I did an
act of מזיק, Mazik
I was אונס, ones, I also can't say that I did an
act of eating תרומה, Truma, like it was all forced on me,
right? So if you can't reverse it, the question is clear, why
is there any discussion of any חיוב chiyuv here? But if you
can reverse it, what's the גמרא's Gemara question? So spit it back
out. Okay, but I'm not spitting it back out and that's exactly
why I'm doing an act of eating and מזיק mazik or eating
and גניבה Gneiva at the same time.
So what exactly is going on?
רש"י Rashi says that the point is that if you can spit
it back out, it seems like the choosing not to spit it
back out is that very choice, I'm not going to spit it
back out, that's already the act of גניבה. Gneiva. And therefore the
swallowing later, which is the act of חייב מיתה, chayev misa, is
actually the second stage. It's not the act of swallowing that's the
act of the גניבה, Gneiva, it's the fact that I am not
spitting it out which is the act of גניבה. Gneiva. That's like
if you take your Casio watch and put it on my dining
room table and I do not do anything with it, I let
it sit there. Right. Am I a גנב? ganav? Maybe. That's a
similar question, right? Right, right, basically. I'm choosing not to return it
and right, I don't have to do a physical act, let it
sit there, I don't touch it. Right, so let's see how the
גמרא Gemara continues. Now the question about why the first one isn't
חייב chayev is because we're assuming that as long as you could
spit it back out if it's still going to be returned like
in reasonable state, which is of course a bizarre assumption, we'll see
what the גמרא's Gemara answer is, then the first one hasn't yet
been מזיק mazik. it. Okay, why the first one hasn't been גונב
goneiv it, I don't know, but maybe he could be a גנב
ganav and you could be a מזיק. mazik, Okay. So okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says היכי דמי, Heichi dami, so לא צריכא דמצי
לאהדורה אדי דחק. lo tzricha dematzi leahadura adei dechak. Now the case
is you could do it but with difficulty. Now what difference does
that make? So it could mean that the choice not to spit
it out is simply is not considered an act of גניבה, Gneiva,
it's going to be so difficult, right, you're not an אונס, ones,
but on the other hand we're not going to call it an
act of גניבה, Gneiva, and it's only the actual swallowing which you're
doing an act which is the act of גניבה. Gneiva. רש"י Rashi
says that what it means is that even were you to spit
it out, it would already be disgusting and wouldn't be worth anything.
Okay. And since it would be disgusting and not worth anything, therefore
you can't be a גנב ganav by not spitting it out because
it's already disgusting. So of course the question is one minute, it's
already disgusting and also תוספות Tosafot points out and therefore your friend
already was the מזיק, mazik because he stuck it in your mouth
to the point that it got disgusting. So if you can't be
the מזיק mazik because it's already disgusting and he's already the מזיק
mazik. or he's already the גנב, ganav, so what am I חייב
chayev for when I swallow it? What type of a חיוב would
there be? So רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both introduce this idea
based on another גמרא Gemara whatever of הנאת מעיו, hana'as meiav, that
even which means the pleasure of your stomach, which means that even
if you did not do anything wrong, the fact that you actually
derived benefit from something that was your friend's demands restitution. So for
example, let's say I don't know, let's say I had a big
pile of fertilizer in my yard and a wind came and it
blew it into your yard and it sank into the ground, it
got trampled on and now your whole crops got fertilized. You didn't
do anything wrong, I didn't do anything wrong, whatever, but bottom line
is you got all this benefit from my stuff. Are you like
exempt? So no, there's an idea that because you derived benefit in
some way that that abstract idea the benefit, the same way if
your if your ball rolled into my yard I'd have to give
it back, so here your benefit rolled into my yard and I
have to give it back. I don't have to give back the
cost of the object but I do have to give back some
way of computing how much benefit I received from that object. So
let me understand, I don't have to pay for the cost of
the fertilizer? I don't have to pay you for the cost of
the fertilizer, I have to pay you for assuming the dollar value
on the benefit received is less than the cost of the fertilizer
itself, okay, because let's say some of it went to waste and
whatever whatever it was, right, I pay you for the actual benefit,
the dollar value we put on the amount of benefit. What if
I benefit more? Then I only pay you for the fertilizer, right.
So therefore רש"י Rashi says you can't be doing an act of
מזיק. mazik It was already מזיק mazik and גנב ganav because the
guy stuck it in and was already disgusting and you're not doing
any damage to it. But when you swallow it, even if you
received benefit from something that belonged to your friend, so therefore you
have to pay. But wait, what about the other guy? What does
the other guy pay? And nothing? So the other guy also חייב
chayav. but maybe he's ran away and you can't prosecute him, I
mean there could be multiple people you could bring to court for
the same thing. Okay, so we're not going to worry about that,
that's a בבא קמא Bava Kama discussion. All right, so anyway, so
therefore, therefore you should pay for the benefit but that will be
overridden by the principle of קים ליה, Kim Lei but. the reality
of benefit only comes about because it went into your stomach, okay?
So we've created a scenario where you're choosing to do an act,
you're choosing to swallow, you didn't have to swallow, but there's no
מזיק mazik and there's no liability that could be talked about until
it went down into your stomach and there it's the liability of
deriving benefit. When you're choosing to swallow, you're also חייב מיתה בידי
שמים chayav mita bidei shamayim because you're choosing to eat תרומה. terumah.
Right, exactly. Even though it's אגב דחאק, agav d'chak, right. Okay, so
okay. רב פפא אמר כגון שתחבו לו חבירו משקין של תרומה לתוך
פיו. Rav Pappa amar kigon shetachvo lo chaveiro mashkin shel terumah letoch
piv. It's liquids of תרומה. terumah. Why does that make it any
different? So רש"י Rashi just says liquids are basically the same idea,
that liquids are stuff that is disgusting as soon as you put
it in somebody's mouth, nobody wants to drink anybody else's, you know,
regurgitated liquid. So therefore there's not going to be a חיוב of
מזיק mazik or גנב ganav at that stage. It's going to be
the friend that's going to have the חיוב, but you're going to
swallow it, and at the time of swallowing, then it's an act
when it hits your stomach, there's the issue of deriving benefit, and
that's a payment that should be appropriate for that, and then there's
also the act of אכילה, achilah, and those two come at the
same time. I get it. And what were we trying, what was
our broader question that we were trying to answer? We're trying now,
we gave a scenario of קים ליה Kim Lei. with a חיוב
מיתה בידי שמים chiyuv mita bidei shamayim of תרומה terumah within the
discussion of רב נחוניא בן הקנה Rav Nechunya ben HaKanah that you
say קים ליה Kim Lei, even by כרת, even by non-מיתת בית
דין. mitat beit din. But what this has now allowed us to
do is get onto a new topic, and the discussion of the
new topic is: when do you say that the two acts are
really one act and one overrides the other, and when do you
say that they're distinct? And right now the גמרא Gemara has identified
them as being distinct if they connect separate moments of time, even
if they're only separated by like a split second, okay? But if
the, and even if they, one like flows from the other, okay,
they're still, as long as they're separate places on the timeline, they're
considered distinct and you don't say קים ליה. Dov, you had a
question? No, hold. Okay. רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar, oh we
just did that. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי אמר,
Rav Ashi amar, no, now you gave up the ghost. רב אשי
אמר בזר שאכל תרומה משלו וקרע שיראין של חבירו. Rav Ashi amar
bezar she'achal terumah mishelo v'kara shirayin shel chaveiro. Okay, completely different story.
You're not מזיק by eating the תרומה. terumah. What you are doing
is, you're, the תרומה terumah is your תרומה, terumah, okay? Some כהן
Kohen gave you תרומה, terumah, whatever you were planning on selling it,
it's your תרומה, terumah, but as you're chomp-chomp, you're walking down the
street and you're chewing your תרומה terumah and you're at the same
time you're ripping your friend's nice silk garment, okay? So therefore, that
happens at the exact same time. Now this answer seems completely bizarre
because it's like, okay, אשרי כוחך, ashrei kochacha, you managed to get
them happening at the same exact point on the timeline, but they're
two completely different acts, right? They're two completely unrelated acts. So give
me a break. If I had to choose which one more I
would say the principle of קים ליה and one thing overshadows the
other, it's this case of chewing and swallowing and whatever where it's
all part of the same process, even if they're not at the
same point of the timeline. רב אשי Rav Ashi seems to feel
that no, that doesn't matter, the only thing that matters is that
they happened at the same second. And if they happened at the
same second, even if I'm doing one thing with my left hand
and one thing with my right hand—with this hand I am turning
on the lights on שבת or יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and with
this hand I am going and breaking a vase—so they're happening at
the same time, or with this mouth I'm eating תרומה, terumah, whatever,
then that exempts me, even though they're completely different acts. Okay? Very
bizarre position, really takes that the only criteria is that they happen
at the same moment in time. What's nice about that is that
no other third party is involved, like the guy stuck it into
my mouth. In other words, you're totally... yeah, right, it takes you
away from the absurd cases of the גמרא Gemara before. But it's
but yes, yes, as a way of describing this case. But conceptually,
to say that we would apply קים ליה when you happen to
be doing two different things at the same time is a... the
idea of קים ליה is hard enough. But it's one thing to
say, if I go ahead and burn down a haystack, you the
court have to decide how you're going to look at this. Are
you going to prosecute this as a capital crime or are you
going to prosecute this as a civil crime? Okay? If I'm doing
two different things at the same time, why should one override the
other? Right? All right, so let's take a look. גופא, Gufa, now
we're going to get into this. We're going to go a little
bit further, okay? אמר רב חסדא מודה רבי נחוניא בן הקנה בגונב
חלבו של חבירו ואכלו שהוא חייב שכבר נתחייב בגניבה קודם שיבוא לידי
איסור חלב. Amar Rav Chisda modeh Rabbi Nechunya ben HaKanah begonve chelvo
shel chaveiro v'achalo shehu chayav shekevar nitchayev bigniva kodem sheyavo lidei issur
cheilev. Okay, when they happen to... again, if you stole and then
you ate it, they're different points in the time and therefore you
are off the hook—er, not off the hook, actually the opposite, you
don't say קים ליה and you're חייב. chayav לימא פליגא דרבי אבין?
Leima pliga d'Rabbi Avin? Let's say this argues on רבי אבין. Rabbi
Avin. דאמר רבי אבין, D'amar Rabbi Avin, הזורק חץ, hazorek chetz, if
somebody shoots an arrow, מתחילת ארבע לסוף ארבע—it's mitchilat arba l'sof arba
הזורק hazorek not היורה, hayoreh, but anyway—הזורק חץ מתחילת ארבע לסוף ארבע,
hazorek chetz mitchilat arba l'sof arba, from the beginning of the four
אמות amot to the end of four אמות, amot, it traverses four
אמות amot in רשות הרבים reshut harabim on שבת, וקרע שיראין בהליכתה,
v'kara shirayin bahalichata, and in the traversing of the four אמות amot
in רשות הרבים reshut harabim on שבת, it tore through somebody's beautiful
garment, right, along the way as it was flying in mid-air. So
the הלכה halacha is פטור, you're... exempt, we say קים ליה and
the חיוב שבת Chiyuv Shabbos overrides the תשלומין. Why? Even though the
חיוב שבת Chiyuv Shabbos only came later when the arrow landed, nevertheless
שעקירה צורך הנחה היא, She-akira tzorech hanacha hi, so because the picking
up of the arrow is part of the process that leads to
it being put down. Okay, so meaning now the obvious point about
how this is different is going to be is- should be obvious.
If anybody knows הלכות שבת, Hilchos Shabbos, the key functions or the
key components of an act of carrying is עקירה Akira (picking the
object up), traversing it four אמות Amos from רשות היחיד Reshus Hayachid
to רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim and then putting it down, הנחה. Hanacha.
So what it is saying is even though the עבירה Aveira doesn't
end until the arrow lands, when did the עבירה Aveira start? When
the arrow was picked up, right, when it was shot, right. You
need both of- you need that whole process to be considered the
מעשה עבירה. Maaseh Aveira. So even though- so you don't look at
the end of the מעשה, Maaseh, you look at the whole מעשה
עבירה. Maaseh Aveira. The whole מעשה עבירה Maaseh Aveira incorporates the time
in the middle when it tore the clothes. Okay, so that's a
very logical position. It did occur at the same time at the
time of the process of the עבירה. Aveira. But the גמרא Gemara
thinks that maybe any physical thing that's a process, even if it's
not legally the same process, should be the same. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: הכא נמי הגבהה צורך אכילה היא. Hacha nami
hagbaha tzorech achila hi. Here too, why don't we say the same
idea? When you picked it up and ate it, the picking it
up was for the purpose of eating it. Alright, now that's obviously
very different. That's saying, okay, in practice it's one process, but legally
it's obviously different things. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara is saying maybe
we should say since the picking it up- you picked it up
to put it in your mouth, we'll see that all as the
same process. So the גמרא Gemara says what- one minute, היכי השתא?
Heichi hashta? You can't compare this. התם אי אפשר להנחה בלא עקירה.
Hasam ee efshar l'hanacha b'lo akira. There, first of all, physically you
cannot put it down unless you picked it up. Again, that's not
even saying it's legally the same act. It's just saying that you
physically can't do the end without the beginning. הכא אפשר לאכילה בלא
הגבהה. Hacha efshar l'achila b'lo hagbaha. Here you can eat something without
picking it up. דבעי גחין ואכיל. De-ba-ee gachin v'achil. You could just
crouch down and eat it on the ground. You don't have to
pick it up. אי נמי. Ee nami. Okay, so that's one difference.
One difference is that it's only when it's- an act that actually
the first part was a necessary part of it, not when you
happened to pick it up but you didn't have to. אי נמי,
Ee nami, or what is probably the better answer, התם אי בעי
לאהדורי לא מצי מהדר לה. Hasam ee ba-ee l'ahadorei lo matzi me-hadar
lei. Actually, even this isn't the same answer. There, if you wanted
to retrieve it, you couldn't retrieve it. You couldn't stop the arrow
in mid-flight. הכא מצי מהדר ליה. Hacha matzi me-hadar lei. Here, after
you pick it up, you could stop it in the middle. So
actually it's quite interesting because the two answers the גמרא Gemara said,
neither of which are the simple sense of the statement. The simple
sense of the statement is that when it comes to חילול שבת,
the act is not just defined by the end of the process.
The act starts by the beginning of the process. The legal עבירה,
Aveira, the legal definition of the act of the עבירה Aveira began
at the beginning of the process. And therefore anything in the middle
is part of the מעשה עבירה. Maaseh Aveira. But the גמרא Gemara
is bracketing the legal definition and just focusing on the physical reality.
Sometimes you have something which is seen as a physical as one
continuous process and- and therefore anything in the way would also say
קים ליה. But the גמרא Gemara says that would only be under
certain circumstances. Either the beginning part was- was necessary to get to
the end, not legally necessary, but practically physically necessary. Or that when
the process began, it couldn't be interrupted. Then you can say- so
if you had a string attached to the arrow and you could
have pulled it back, it would be different according to this. Or
if you were walking in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim in four אמות,
Amos, then it would be different because you could have chosen to
stop in the middle. Okay, so it's not about the legal definition.
We do concede that it will be a physical thing which will
say is one continuous process and you'll say קים ליה, but that's
only if the beginning is either necessary or that the process cannot
be interrupted. Let's just read one more line. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: מאי איכא בין האי לישנא להאי לישנא? Mai eika
bein hai lishna l'hai lishna? What difference would there be which one,
which way you say it? So איכא בינייהו, Eika beineiyhu, what I
just said, מעביר סכין ברשות הרבים וקרע שיראין בהליכתו. Maavir sakin b'reshus
harabim v'kara shirayin b'halichato. You're actually taking a- walking a knife, not
shooting an arrow, through רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim on שבת and you're
tearing these nice fine garments. להך לישנא דאמרת אי אפשר להנחה בלא
עקירה, L'hach lishna d'amrat ee efshar l'hanacha b'lo akira, according to the
one that says that you can't put it down without picking it
up, הכא נמי אי אפשר להנחה בלא עקירה. Hacha nami ee efshar
l'hanacha b'lo akira. Here too, you can't have the end of the
process without the beginning of the process.
You've got to pick it up or else you'll never transport it
four אמות Amos in רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. You don't have a
הנחה Hanacha because you can walk around רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim the
whole time. But you did have a הנחה Hanacha which made it
חילול שבת.
להך לישנא דאמרת לא מצי מהדר
ליה,
L'hach lishna d'amrat lo matzi
me-hadar
lei, but according to the idea that
it's one process because it can't be interrupted because it- once you
start it, it will necessarily finish, הכא מצי מהדר ליה. Hacha matzi
me-hadar lei.
Here you could interrupt it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, seems to
be- both
answers are about the physical reality of defining one process, either because
it- it can't be interrupted or because the beginning was just practically
physically necessary. Although personally I would rather say that the first answer
that says אי אפשר לעקירה בלא הנחה Ee efshar l'akira b'lo hanacha
is more of a legal point, that legally it's not considered an
act of carrying something in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim unless it has
the first part of it. And therefore any time where the first-
where the beginning of the process is part of the מעשה עבירה
Maaseh Aveira as halachically defined, then we'll call it all one process.
But if it's not part of the הלכה... Halacha... By שבת, yeah.
Right, by שבת. So what about the concept of גמר מלאכה, gmar
melacha, that there's no חיוב until it's a גמר? gmar? No, no,
that's exactly the point. You're not חייב chayav, until it's done, but
the process begins when you... when you... So you're not חייב, chayav
I misunderstood then, you're not חייב chayav once you... No, no, but
the legal beginning of the process. If I put something in the
oven, I'm not חייב chayav, until it cooks, okay? But the מעשה
עבירה ma'aseh aveirah began from the time I put it in the
oven. We don't say that the מעשה עבירה ma'aseh aveirah I did
when it cooks, okay? The מעשה עבירה ma'aseh aveirah began from the
time I put it in the oven. It's just I'm not חייב,
it doesn't finish until a certain point. But the legal definition of
the act of the חילול שבת was the putting it on the
fire and then right? So you cannot do a מעשה הוצאה... ma'aseh
hotza'ah... Right, fine, if you put the bread in the oven five
minutes before שבת is over, the מעשה עבירה ma'aseh aveirah started on
שבת. It doesn't finish cooking until after... So there's a... so there's
a מחלוקת machlokes about that, because... so anyway, but the basic point
is, is that the basic point is, is that when the גמרא
says עקירה צורך הנחה, akirah tzorech hanachah, is it speaking about the
physical aspect of it, which it sounds like from the גמרא, or
it's talking about the legal aspect which I think makes a lot
more sense. That if legally this is part of the מעשה עבירה,
ma'aseh aveirah, the עקירה, akirah, then obviously we're going to see it
as one continuous act. What time will be?